Finding Aid for Myers in Germany World War II Collection
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
Rowland Myers Germany in World War II Collection 1933-1942
Myers, Rowland M.
1 Linear Feet (1 record center box)
myers
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from Lt. Rowland Myers, circa 1946
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
According to his obituary, Rowland M. Myers was born in Brooklyn in 1907, and received his bachelor's degree from Dartmouth College in 1928. He earned a Ph.D. in Romance Languages and Literature from Johns Hopkins University in 1931, then taught Romance Languages at Union College and the University of Texas before World War II. During the war, he served in "Army intelligence," but the exact nature of his service is not known. In 1946, his mailing address was for the Internal Affairs and Communication Division of the OMGUS (Office of Military Government, United States), the office governing the U.S. controlled sections of Germany at the close of World War II.
During and after World War II, the University of Michigan mounted an effort to document the war's history, and soldiers were encouraged to donate materials to what was named the "University War Collection." According to F. Clever Bald, the University War Historian, writing in 1946: "The response of alumni to requests for printed materials relating to the war has surpassed all expectations. A veritable avalanche of books, leaflets, newspapers, broadsides, posters, and other important documents poured into the office of the War Historian from all the fighting fronts. More than 5,000 books and thousands of newspapers and other items have been received."[1]
In 1943 Lt. Rowland M. Myers, who had apparently attended the Judge Advocate General's School at the University of Michigan for a summer, began shipping (via government freight) crates of German books, newspapers, and pamphlets to the University. Many fo the books were incorporated directly into the general collection with a bookplate attributing Myers as the donor. The pamphlets were later placed in the University's Department of Rare Books and Special Collections (now the Special Collections Library), where they were merged with similar materials, including the 1960 purchase of the Ludendorff collection of approximately 400 books and pamphlets.
Although it is not mentioned in any correspondence, Myers also sold to the University five linear feet of documents and publications apparently seized from a local office of the Nazi party in Eisenach, Germany. Little attention was paid to these materials until 1959, when Gerhard L. Weinberg joined the faculty. Weinberg had served as a research analyst for the War Documentation Project at Columbia University and as the director of the American Historical Association Project for Microfilming Capture German Documents. Weinberg pulled out the archives from the materials sent by Myers, creating a brief inventory entitled "German Archival Material in the Rare Book Room" where he described them thus: "There are the files of Hermann Köhler, the Kreisleiter der NSDAP, Kreis Eisenach. Included is correspondence, notes, incoming and outgoing mimeographed circulars, special and secret publications from Köhler's files, and albums of photographs."
Subjects:
Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei; Germany -- History -- 1933-1945; Myers, Rowland M.
- Series I. Hans Frank Materials
  - Photograph Album, Wahlkampf 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Undated Album (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jahresabschluss 1939/NS Rechtswahrerbund e.V, 42 Pages (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II. Gefechtsberichten 1941
  - Gefechts-Bericht der 1. Gebirgs-Division über die Verfolgungskämpfe Winniza-Golowanewsk und die Vernichtungs-Schlacht von Podwissokoje (Uman) June 21 - August 7, 1941, 53 Pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gefechts-Bericht der 1. Gebirgs-Division übergang über den Dnjepr – Die Schlacht von Antonowka Verfolgung in der Steppe – Der Kampf am Panzergraben - Der Durchbruch über den Tschingul – Die Schlacht am Mogila Tokmak September 6 - October 10, 1941, 102 Pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Karte 1:100,000 zum Gefechts-Bericht der 1. Gebirgs-Division September 6 - October 10, 1941, 3 Sheets (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III. Malmédy materials 1940-1944
  - Miscellaneous papers of the Kreisbauernschaft Malmedy 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Haushaltssatzung des Landkreises Malmedy für das Rechnungsjahr 1941 1941, 103 Pages (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Stellenplan der Kreiskommunalverwaltung Malmedy nach dem Stande vom 1, Januar 1942" 1942, 5 Pages (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Auftragsbuch I" 1943-44 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Auftragsbuch II" 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series IV. Christmas materials for troops 1939-1941
  - Kreigsweinacht des W. B. Kdo. Siegen 1939, 40 Pages (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Kreigs-Weinachten 1940, 58 Pages (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [Kreigsweinachten] 1941, 29 Pages (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Festfolgel!" 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series V. Recruiting Materials
  - "Rekruten-Ausbildung" April 1936 - September 1936, 45 Pages (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Recruiting materials for the Waffen-SS, Ergänzungsstelle West (VI), Düsseldorf 1941, 20 Pages (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Schoolgirl history notebook undated, 64 Pages (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Group of 31 commemorative holy cards and other commemorative items 1827-1934 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Propaganda leaflets, photographs (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Propaganda leaflets, in English (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Propaganda leaflets, in French and miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 24)